Yassmin Abdel-Magied: Do you remember
the first time you heard about
people using chatbots as therapists?
Dr. Rania Awaad: I do.
Yeah, it was actually a patient of mine.
And she said, in between our
sessions, um, I talked to a
chatbot and I said, come again?
Like what, what's going on?
Yassmin Abdel-Magied: Dr. Rania Awad
runs the Muslim mental health and
Islamic psychology lab at Stanford.
And she's the president of Maristan.
Dr. Rania Awaad: Which is a nonprofit
organization dedicated to educating
and clinically serving the Muslim
mental health needs of our communities.
Yassmin Abdel-Magied: And one day, when a
patient of hers walks in and says they've
been using an AI chatbot for therapy.
Dr. Rania Awaad: I started wondering:
is this going to be the end of us?
Psychiatrists and psychologists?
No!
Like, what is the point of all of
these years of training and, you
know, learning how to have that
therapeutic ear and actually help?
13 years of school…
to be replaced by an AI?
No!
Yassmin Abdel-Magied: But then something
made Rania begin to see a world in which
AI and Islamic understandings of mental
health might be able to come together?